Hall, T. mss. II, 1944-1961 LMC 2545
Lilly Library
Hall, T. mss. II
1944-1961
Lilly Library
Hall, Tom (Artist)
LMC 2545
1 Box 1 standard
The Hall, T., mss. II, 1944-1961, consists of correspondence, writings, and drawings by advertising executive and artist Tom Hall, 1880-.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift: 2006
Biographical Note
Tom Hall (1880-) was born in Indianapolis on 19 March 1880, to parents Clara Broughton (1845-1938) and Charles Eli Hall (1850-1910), manager of the Land and Transportation Company of La Gloria, Cuba. Hall attended Yale University for the 1898-1899 academic year but left school to pursue his art and moved to Washington, D.C., where he became the chief illustrator for The Sunday Times. He married Martha Matilda Baird (1876-1966), daughter of Julia Catherine Rogers and Brigadier General George W. Baird (1839-1906), in 1902. In 1903, the couple's son George Baird Hall (1903-1983) was born. Tom Hall moved to New York City in 1904 and joined the staff of Calkins & Holden Advertising Agency. In 1912, he co-founded Churchill-Hall Advertising Agency with Charles E. Churchill (1882-1917). His daughter Rosemary Hall (later Robinson, then Bruning) (1913-1977) was born in 1913. In 1916, Hall returned to Calkins & Holden, where he served in a number of different roles and became vice-president in 1926. Earnest Elmo Calkins (1868-1964), co-founder of Calkins & Holden, wrote that Hall "was in a class by himself, unpredictable and surprising, with an invention and ingenuity almost incredible"; his sense of design, integrating both illustration and typeface, revolutionized the world of advertising. Upon his retirement in the 1940s, Hall began making paper cut-outs of characters from children's books.
Arrangement
The collection is organized according to original order; letters are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes letters Tom Hall exchanged with Lall G. Montgomery (1902-1986) and other book collectors, authors, and clients for his paper cut-out characters; writings, including transcriptions of children's stories and other articles; miscellaneous items, including a photograph and an illustration of Hall's book; a transcription of "The Story of Black Little Sambo" as retold by Elisabeth Woodworth Ball (1897-1982); and Hall's drawings, including a self-portrait as a cat sketched on an undated letter (photocopy only) to Lall G. Montgomery, a caricature drawn on the 7 October 1965 letter to Lall G. Montgomery, and an illustration of Hall's story "The Wonderful Voyage of Old G and Father Tid."
Related Materials
See Hall, T. mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Art; Paper work; Children's literature; Children's literature--Illustrations; Hall, Tom (Artist)
- Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1945-March 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, April 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, May 1946-February 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, March 1948-April 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, June 1949-March 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, n. d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "The Story of Little Black Sambo" (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "The Week in which Alice Liddell Received" (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Transcription, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Foreword, n. d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photograph of Tom Hall, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Illustration of Father Tid (Box 1, Folder 13)